טוב, Tov, today's דף daf is דף כ"א, daf Kaf-Aleph, 21, and
we pick up in the middle of כ' עמוד ב'. Kaf Amud
Beis. We're in the middle of certain statements about astronomically when the
new moon can be seen with the גמרא's Gemara assumption that it
can be seen once it's moved six hours off from the conjunction,
from when it's exactly in line with the sun and the earth.
Although in practice it's really closer to something like 16 to 18
hours. Anyway, and the גמרא's Gemara statement that it's important to know
some of these astronomical facts לחושי סהדי lachushei sahade to contradict the
witnesses in case their witness testifies something to that we know cannot
be possibly true given the astronomical realities. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara picks up and says the following: אמר מר, Amar Mar, about
eight lines from the bottom, line starts with the word סהדי Sahade
on כ' עמוד ב'. Kaf Amud Beis. אמר מר, Amar Mar, so
let's go back and look at a statement we said earlier: צריך
שיהיה לילה ויום מן החודש, Tzarich sheyehei layla veyom min hachodesh, the
night and the day both have to be from the month. Now,
מנלן, minalan, where does what does where do we get this from?
So I guess I'll read the פסוקים psukim and then I'll say
what this means. רבי יוחנן אמר מערב עד ערב, Rabbi Yochanan amar
me'erev ad erev, from evening to evening, right? So that shows you
that a day goes from one evening to the next, it's
night and day combined. וריש לקיש אמר עד יום האחד ועשרים לחודש
בערב, VeReish Lakish amar ad yom ha'echad ve'esrim lachodesh ba'arev, when it
speaks about eating מצות matzos for seven days, it says until the
21st at night, which again shows you that the day extends from
the night before up until and not including the following night, which
is basically just a point that you know a day is considered
to be the night and the day. מאי בינייהו, Mai beinaihu, what's
the difference between those two? Either way you're basically saying it's the
night and the following day. אביי אמר משמע דרשין בינייהו, Abaye amar
mashmach dorshin beinaihu, there's no real halachic difference, it's just a question
of which verse you're learning from. רבא אמר, Rava amar, and רבא
Rava says, חצות לילה איכא בינייהו, chatzos laila ika beinaihu, the difference
is חצות. chatzos. What does it mean חצות? chatzos? Because the verse
that says you eat מצה matza for seven days until the 21st
day, the point though is is that you really ate מצה matza
on the first day and you ate it up until midnight, like
this is assuming that the time of eating the קרבן פסח korban
pesach goes you know goes until midnight, and therefore the time of
eating מצה matza the first night goes until midnight. So that first
night really is cut in half by midnight. Now what does all
of this mean? Let me first before we get to the whole
midnight thing which I'll unpack a little bit more in a minute,
let me just first talk a minute about what we're trying what
is the halachic meaning here about the idea of צריך שיהיה לילה
ויום מן החודש. tzarich sheyehei layla veyom min hachodesh. So what רש"י
Rashi says it means is really a rabbinic point and therefore according
to רש"י Rashi these פסוקים psukim have to be pure אסמכתות. asmachtos.
What רש"י Rashi says it means is is that if you see
the new moon excuse me the old moon on a given night,
you cannot go ahead and say that later that day is ראש
חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Now that's obviously astronomically true because as we said
the גמרא Gemara said earlier from the old from the last sliver
of the old moon to the new sliver of the new moon
is at least 24 hours. For 24 hours the moon is hidden.
Actually as I said it's really closer to 36, but fine we'll
work with 24. Okay, so obviously if you saw the little bit
of the old moon the night before, there's no way you're going
to see the new moon the next day during the daytime of
the following day. So why do you need a פסוק pasuk and
what's the whole point? So רש"י Rashi says the whole point is
to tell בית דין, Beis Din, remember we were talking until now
and we'll continue to talk a little bit about how בית דין
Beis Din can manipulate the calendar in contrast to the astronomical realities,
so רש"י Rashi says the point is to say to בית דין
Beis Din don't do don't manipulate the calendar and make the daytime
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh if the night before the old moon was
seen. Why? Because that'll just be patently obvious to people that you're
manipulating it. People will have seen the old moon the night before,
it'll be clearly like a lie and a fraud to see you
making the daytime on the day to say oh we saw the
new moon and we're going to make it ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
So according to רש"י Rashi it's only the type of a concern
of how does it appear to the people and so on, it's
really not a biblical issue and therefore the פסוקים psukim here are
just an אסמכתא. asmachta. What does the idea of חצות chatzos mean
for רש"י? Rashi? For חצות chatzos means the question of according to
the second opinion well maybe if you saw it the night before
before חצות chatzos then it's already early enough that you could make
the next that you could make the daytime you could declare it
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. If you saw it after חצות chatzos then
clearly already it'll be so obvious to people you can't. So that's
the issue for רש"י Rashi whether if it's is it obvious enough
can we make it ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh if the old moon
was seen the night before. רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says a different
explanation which works a little bit better in why it's quoting a
verse and he says what's going on here is the question of
whether the entire מולד molad has to be on the day that
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh you know whether the day that ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh is
declared Look, let's say here that right here's the right from the
time of the מולד molad right so the מולד molad is basically
when you know the moon has just moved like an infinitesimal away
from the conjunction right so in theory I mean it's not really
visible because the sun is too you know is too close obviously
it's overshadowed by the sun but in theory it's now into the
new moon phase it's off of the conjunction okay? So for this
period of the מולד molad until the point when it's visible the
גמרא Gemara has been saying it's six hours in practice it's really
more like 18 hours okay? So this is the מולד molad visible
will occur six to 18 hours later okay is when it goes
from the מולד molad to being visible because now 18 hours later
it's a little even more removed and now you actually can start
to see the sliver of the new moon.
Is that why when you when you announce the מולד molad for
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh the מולד molad is always announced as being
as happening the day before it's going to be ראש חודש?
Rosh Chodesh? Yeah because the מולד molad is just it's not a
visible reality it's an astronomical reality of moving off of the conjunction
and besides the fact that the calendar gets adjusted as we know
and isn't always in sync with the moon is the fact that
you cannot actually see the new moon until according to the גמרא
Gemara six hours in practice more like 18 hours after after the
מולד. molad. Now let's say we went ahead and we said
let's say we went ahead and said that today I don't know
let's say we said today Monday is ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh okay
why is today ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh? Today is ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh because sometime in Monday we saw we saw the new moon
I don't know if that's even pointed in the right direction we'll
get to that in the second פרק perek sometime Monday we saw
the new moon okay. Now when we saw the new moon on
Monday now by the way let's remind ourselves when is the new
moon visible the new moon becomes visible right the moon is moving
counterclockwise to the sun so it becomes a new moon when it
moves off of its counterclockwise okay so therefore at the new moon
you've got sunrise and after sunrise you've got the moon
following alright now that is going to not really be visible because
it's coming right you know the sun is like so close to
it maybe later in the month you know you know there'll be
a bigger bit of a gap and it won't be bright enough
but to see it right after sunrise right when it's a new
moon you're not going to see it it's following too close to
the sun okay but right after sunset you will see it you'll
see it in the beginning of the night okay. So you will
see the new moon at the beginning of the night and then
as the month progresses you know the moon travels more behind so
you might see it a little bit after sunrise and you might
see it for like more of the night because it's traveling more
behind.
Why is it traveling behind the sun?
I never understood it. So to speak. Yeah I don't know okay
but that has to do with somebody can correct me rotation of
the I'm sure it has to do with rotation of the moon
rotation of the earth I'm not figuring that out right now let's
just accept that. Okay so you went ahead and now you've decided
that Monday was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh right that meant that basically
right it was going to it was visible you know if it
was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh it means witnesses came and they testified
they saw the new moon right that means that it was visible
if they saw the moon if Monday is ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
it means that they saw the new moon
night
and day they saw the new moon let's say at 7:00 PM
on Monday night okay and therefore they're going to come in the
morning and they're going to say we saw the new moon last
night great let's make Monday ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh okay. So the
question is right when did the מולד molad when did the מולד
molad occur?
So in this case right they saw the new moon here on
Monday night right the מולד molad which occurred six to eight hours
before right the מולד molad had to have occurred like way before
had to have occurred on Sunday because it was like six to
eight hours before the moon six
to eight or 18
six to eight or 18 whatever anyway at least six hours before
on Sunday so that means that the מולד molad occurred way back
here right so therefore this new day Monday which is ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh all of it is in the is from the new
moon meaning all of Monday right is during this new moon period
because all of it came after the מולד molad occurred because this
occurred Sunday and if they saw the new moon 7:00 PM then
the מולד molad occurred at least at like I mean 7:00 PM
the מולד molad occurred at least like 1:00 PM on Sunday right
so all of the new moon is after the מולד. molad. That's
כולו יום מן החודש kulo yom min hachodesh okay which means that
the day you're going to make ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh it's not
enough that the new moon that the moon just came visible but
part of it was related to the old moon no it all
has to have been part of the new moon. Now you'll say
well that'll always be the case right? But maybe not and again
somebody here can correct me right maybe not necessarily. Necessarily, meaning maybe
you didn't see the moon on Monday night. Maybe what you actually
did is you saw the moon on Monday day. Maybe it started
trailing enough behind the sun that it actually was visible at the
beginning of Monday day. Is everybody here sort of with me? So
you actually saw the new moon Monday day
at like 7:00 a.m. let's say. Okay? So then you're going to
come later that day and testify we saw the new moon this
morning. It was trailing so far behind we saw the Oh okay,
but you saw the new moon that morning, when was the מולד?
molad? All right? If you saw the moon in the morning, the
מולד molad in this case was six hours before was 1:00 a.m.
Right? Still Monday.
Yes! But that means part of Monday night was
the old moon.
Okay? Right? If the מולד molad was 1:00 a.m. then part of
Monday night was the old moon. So according to רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu
Chananel the way he reads the גמרא Gemara is well you can't
make Monday ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh because the whole part of Monday
has to have been after the מולד. molad.
Have I lost you? You got it? So now it could be
that you saw the moon 7:00 a.m. because the מולד molad was
actually 6:00 p.m. or 5:00 p.m. on Sunday, right? So it was
5:00 p.m. on Sunday that was way too late for it to
be visible. It was only one hour removed yeah it was way
too late for it to be visible there and it became visible
here. Well that's fine because all of Monday right which starts at
6:00 p.m. was post-מולד. molad. But in a case where the מולד
molad occurred
at 1:00 a.m. and it only became visible here, so part of
Monday was pre-מולד. molad. So רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says you can't
make ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh unless the entire day of ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh is post-מולד. molad. Now תוספות Tosafot disagrees. תוספות Tosafot says
that's not in practice what we do. We don't actually care when
the מולד molad was all we care about is when it was
visible. But that's the way he reads it and therefore it makes
sense that you're looking at פסוקים pesukim and saying like the entire
day has to be post-מולד. molad.
Yes? I just want to clarify in light of what you're saying,
independent of the הרז"ה. Ha-Razah. What did they do in practice? In
practice they would declare ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh in the morning and
למפרע l'mafrea it had been No,
they had to accept witnesses that day. So if it was that
they saw the moon the beginning of the night, witnesses would travel
at night they'd come the next day sometime before the following sunset
and testify we saw it last night which is halachically the same
day and they'd say okay today becomes ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Or
in this scenario where it was trailing enough behind and they saw
it early in the morning, they'll come and as long as they
come before nightfall they said we saw it this morning okay so
today is ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
But what about last night? Because I saw today's ראש חודש, Rosh
Chodesh, we saw it last night. Right. So that means when they
testify in the morning למפרע l'mafrea it had been ראש חודש. Rosh
Chodesh.
Now we discover that yes this entire day is ראש חודש.
Rosh
Chodesh.
You're always making the day itself ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. You're always
realizing it's ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh in the middle of ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh.
So when we say יעלה ויבוא Yaaleh V'yavo at night there may
have been in a situation where they would not have said whatever
the appropriate prayers were that night.
Right, which is one of the reasons by the way that you
don't go back in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei if you missed יעלה
ויבוא Yaaleh V'yavo at night. Because you don't accept קידוש החודש Kiddush
Hachodesh at night and that therefore night anyway at least the first
night of ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, if it's a two-day ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh you know the night will be, but on the first
day ראש right on Monday you don't yet know the night will
be ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh? so it's always in doubt tonight.
Okay anyway that's the point of רבינו חננאל. Rabbeinu Chananel.
Now with our fixed calendar now, yes? Is there a gap between
what we calculate to be the מולד molad and when we declare
ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh Yes, yes.
Yeah, I mean I don't I can't tell you exactly but yes,
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh was never on the I mean unless by
chance due to manipulation but in real testimony the ability to recognize
that it was a new moon always occurred hours after the מולד,
molad, like I said according to the גמרא Gemara six hours and
in practice it's closer to eighteen hours after the מולד molad only
then the moon becomes visible.
So our fixed calendar works that way?
Our fixed well our fixed calendar constantly is getting adjusted for various
reasons as we saw. But when you now you
announce the מולד, molad, you say the מולד molad will be you
know twelve hours and sixteen חלקים chalakim after one and ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh is the next day.
Right. Now you know why. Exactly. Now you know why. Yes. Now
you know why. Yes.
When we announce that the מולד molad is Jerusalem time do you
think there's something there about so we're saying it's not בבל Bavel
time in terms of that one hour difference.
Oh maybe maybe. I just think it's because קידוש החודש Kiddush Hachodesh
happened in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and we want to sort of
anchor that sort of thing in the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael reality.
Okay so that's basically the point and therefore the רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu
Chananel says this point here about the the idea of חצות Chatzot
was this question about the... Well, what if the מולד Molad happened
in this case, the מולד Molad happened after חצות Chatzos so part
of the old month pre-מולד Molad period was already after חצות. Chatzos.
But according but let's say the מולד Molad happened at 11:00 PM
so although part of the evening was pre-מולד, Molad, since from חצות
Chatzos onward it was post-מולד, Molad, you're good. And that's how he
reads the issue of the חצות. Chatzos. Does the whole night have
to be post-מולד Molad or just the or just post-חצות Chatzos have
to be post the מולד? Molad? And part of the issue is
is that because the way he understands it, since we eat מצה
Matzah the first night before חצות, Chatzos, but it's part of the
fulfillment this is the way רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel reads it different
than רש״י, Rashi, part of the fulfillment of the idea of eating
מצה Matzah seven days so it's like we ate מצה Matzah the
entire day even though we only ate it before חצות, Chatzos, you
see that having just some time you know just having a little
time before חצות Chatzos is enough to count for the entire day.
Again, it's not exactly, but the basic point being is that since
that idea of the seven days really there's a pre-חצות Chatzos and
a post-חצות Chatzos period on the first night, according to that he
says as long as as long as the entire period post-חצות Chatzos
is of the post-מולד Molad you're good. Let's go on in the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, said רבי זירא, Rabbi
Zeira,
אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, כל ספיקא לקמיה שדינן, Kol sefeika
lekamei shadinan, now we leave astronomy for a little bit and we
talk about and we talk about I mean still realities of קידוש
החודש Kiddush Hachodesh but about dealing with the fact that we're in
בבל Bavel and we don't know when they made the new moon
when they made the new months. Now again, remember the key months
that matter are תשרי Tishrei and ניסן. Nissan. And in תשרי Tishrei
and ניסן Nissan the month before them אדר Adar and אלול Elul
we learned are as a standard 29 days. So given let's assume
we're going to assume the month before was 29 days, so that
would mean let's say ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh would be on Sunday,
okay, but there's a possibility the previous month was 30 days so
it would mean that ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh would be on Monday.
So what we're going to but as a but sort of we're
going to assume Sunday. So if we're going to assume Sunday what's
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh then two weeks from Sunday will be a
Sunday will be the 15th, will be סוכות Succos or פסח. Pesach.
So if we're going to observe another day ספיקא דיומא, Sefeika deyoma,
it's going to be Sunday and Monday, right, because ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh we're assuming Sunday but the previous month might have been a
30-day month, there's always that chance which would make push everything off
a day. So so he's going to say, well what about the
possibility that actually ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh started a day earlier than
now? You're telling me how could
it start a day earlier?
If the only issue was so here
we have so we have אב, Av, אלול, Elul, תשרי, Tishrei, okay.
So we're assuming אב Av is 30 days, אלול Elul was 29,
okay, it doesn't really matter how many days תשרי Tishrei is. We're
assuming אלול Elul was 29 days, so we're going to make ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah on a Sunday assuming 29, but in case it
was 30 then that'll push everything off and that'll turn it into
a Monday. But what about the possibility that אלול Elul was 29
days but you know what also maybe if we're not having the
fixed calendar and we're doing it based on testimony, maybe אב Av
was 29 days and we didn't hear about that. So maybe actually
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah should have been שבת. Shabbos. Why do we
why are we only concerned about this being 30 days and not
concerned about that being 29?
Then you should keep on going back and back and back אדר,
Adar, right.
So let's right, so
let's take a look.
So that's part of the answer because that you would have found
out by then which is essentially what the גמרא Gemara is going
to say. Let's take a look. אמר רבי זירא אמר רב נחמן,
Amar Rabbi Zeira Amar Rav Nachman, כל ספיקא לקמיה שדינן, Kol sefeika
lekamei shadinan, any doubt is you know is goes forward, meaning maybe
we start a day later because the last month was 30 days.
למימרא, Lemeimra, so the גמרא Gemara says this says דחמיסר ושיתסר עבדינן,
Dechamiser veshitser avdinan,
we'll make 15th and 16th יום טוב Yom Tov because it's a
ספק, Safek, maybe it's a day later 16th. ארבעסר לא עבדינן, Arba'asar
lo avdinan, but we won't make the 14th, we won't be concerned
that we started that we that we actually started late and actually
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, was a day earlier and we should make
the 14th into יום טוב. Yom Tov. The גמרא Gemara says וליעבדי
נמי ארבעסר, Veliavdai nami arba'asar, יומא חסרו לאב וחסרו לאלול. Dyoma chasru
l'Av vechasru l'Elul.
Let's go ahead and say you know maybe the 14th because maybe
both אלול Elul and אב Av were 29 days. Okay, everybody with
me, yeah? דילמא חסרו לאב וחסרו לאלול, Dilma chasru l'Av vechasru l'Elul,
maybe both of these were 29 days. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, תרי ירחי חסירי קלא אית להו, Trei yarchei chasiri kala it
lehu,
everybody would find out if there were two 29-day months right in
a row. רש״י Rashi says when it says everybody would find out
if there were two 29-day months in a row, it does not
mean אב Av and אלול. Elul. You know why? Because here you
are on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you don't have enough time to
find out that אלול Elul was two days, right? Or maybe even
if you're in סוכות Succos maybe that's not enough time, you know,
you're to find out that אלול Elul was 29 days. But there
are another there was אלול Elul 29 days, but there's another month
that was also 29 days. You know what month was also 29
days?
תמוז. Tammuz. By the normal category 29, 30, 29. So if אב
Av had been 29 here a month later whenever אלול... Elul... word
you would have heard that there were two 29 day months back
in אב Av and תמוז. Tammuz. And since you didn't, right, if
so, you obviously אב Av is 30 days. Basically the גמרא Gemara
means which is if if אב Av were 30 days you if
were 29 day you would have found out. Okay, and therefore we
do not have to be concerned that it's earlier
than then the then Sunday, the only thing we have to be
concerned is you know is that it's a day later but don't
have to be concerned that it would be ever be a day
earlier. Yes?
Why don't they just cite the משנה Mishna that says that אלול
Elul is one of the months that they send out?
No, because oh, because you know we're talking about בבל Bavel like
far enough away that they wouldn't have gotten the message. The whole
place is that you do ספיקא דיומא sefeika deyoma in בבל Bavel
are the places that are so distant that you don't get the
message in time. The places that are close enough to have heard
from the שלוחים shluchim they know which day was ראש חודש, Rosh
Chodesh. right? So this is all about the distance places. And that
actually becomes a transition now to discussing exactly that, the places that
didn't get the message.
And so what do they mean, what's the 15th and 16th?
Right, when do you celebrate, when do you celebrate סוכות? Succos? 15th
and 16th. You never say, oh, well, maybe maybe two months ago
it was a חסר, chaser, maybe we should start the 14th. Okay,
because that you would have heard of. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this: לוי איקלע לבבל. Levi ikla le-Bavel. לוי Levi who
came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael dropped in in בבל Bavel בחד
עשר בתשרי, bachad asar be-Tishrei, the 11th of תשרי. Tishrei. Okay, great.
מוצאי יום כיפור, Motzei Yom Kippur, everybody is out building their סוכה.
succah. אמר Amar and he said, בסים תבשילא דבבלאי, bassim tavshila de-Bavla'ei,
the the pots of the Babylonians of you Babylonian Jews are very
like tasty, you're making all this yummy delicious food now in your
kitchens, ביומא רבה דמערבא, beyoma rabba de-Ma'arava, on the day where it's
יום כיפור Yom Kippur in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Oh my god!
So there it was, right, because we don't keep two days of
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. For יום כיפור Yom Kippur we assume that
we know that אלול Elul was 29 days, right, where nobody's being
asked to keep two days of יום כיפור Yom Kippur and everybody
is eating on the 11th. Well, he happened once to say, guess
what guys, they made אלול Elul 30 days and right now it's
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. You guys are all פרעסינג fressing and enjoying
yourself, it's יום כיפור Yom Kippur in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So
אמרי ליה. amrei lei. Yeah, exactly, אמרי ליה. amrei lei. They said
to לוי, Levi, אסהיד, aseid, testify. Don't just סתם stam schmooze. Go
ahead and and present testimony and say, I want to testify that
today is actually יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, I know what happened in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and then we'll stop eating. Okay, do something
about it. אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said to them, לא שמעתי
מפי בית דין מקודש. lo shamati mipi beis din mekudash. No, I
wasn't actually in the presence of the בית דין beis din in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael when they declared it was ראש חודש. Rosh
Chodesh Now, who cares if you say you know the what the
day was? So רש"י Rashi says so what does this mean that
I wasn't there when it declared מקודש? mekudash? So we're going to
see in a minute the גמרא Gemara is going to say that
you have to actually have direct before the שלוחים shluchim go out
to testify when the new month was, they have to have heard
directly the בית דין beis din say מקודש. mekudash. Okay, but there
could be a scenario where you know exactly where where you know
exactly where where you know exactly where ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh when
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, was even if you didn't hear them say
מקודש. mekudash. Why? Because here the whole point was they made it
into a 30 day month. So what happened? All of day 29
passed, excuse me, all of day 30 passed and no witnesses came
and you didn't make day 30 a new month, right? In that
case you know that it'll be a 30 day month and the
next month will be and the next day will be ראש חודש,
Rosh Chodesh. right? Is everybody with me? Day 30 passed at the
בית דין, beis din, no witnesses show up. So obviously therefore it's
a 30 day month and the next day is ראש חודש. Rosh
Chodesh But the הלכה halacha is the witnesses don't go out until
they actually formally hear the next day בית דין beis din I
mean the the messengers don't go out until they formally hear the
next day the witnesses come and בית דין beis din accept the
testimony and say מקודש. mekudash. Even though they know 100 percent that
since yesterday wasn't ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. today is ראש חודש. Rosh
Chodesh You don't send out the messengers till officially you hear that.
We'll hear about that more in a minute. So לוי Levi says,
oh, I can't testify for you even though I know that it
was a 30 day month because no witnesses were accepted on day
30, I know the previous month's 30 day month, I didn't officially
hear them say מקודש mekudash the day before so I won't testify
for you. So תוספות Tosfos goes crazy. He says what the heck
do I care if technically you heard מקודש mekudash and under normal
rules of בית דין beis din the messengers wouldn't go forth. Right
now you know that today is יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So what
does this sort of technicality mean that you're not going to do
something and everybody's going to go ahead and eat on יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? How can you not tell them what they're doing? So
if you take a look, so תוספות Tosfos first tries to create
a scenario where maybe it's not a 100 100 percent that today
was יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Like maybe it was like it was
he says that it was if you take a look תוספות Tosfos
starts by saying תוספות לוי איקלע. Tosfos Levi ikla. He says like
this, he says שיצא, sheyatza,
it's two lines down in the narrow lines, he says שיצא ביום
שלשים של אלול סמוך לחשיכה. sheyatza beyom shloshim shel Elul samuch le-chasheicha.
So לא ישהא ביום lo yashas beyom לבוא לקבל עדות. lavo l'kabel
eidus. So not that he literally left
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael after day thirty had totally passed. He left,
or he left the בית דין, Beis Din, not ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael because it was going to be ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. He
left the בית דין Beis Din twenty minutes before sunset on day
thirty. So in all practical terms, there was absolutely no time for
witnesses to come, for it to be checked out, and to make
that day ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. But he didn't know a hundred,
hundred percent. Who knows? Something totally maybe a one in a million,
maybe they came in a second and they did צ'יק צ'אק chick-chak
and it all took place in five minutes. But okay, for all
intents and purposes, he knew it wasn't ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah on
that day, but he did leave twenty minutes before, so you never
know exactly. Okay, so at least תוספות Tosos doesn't make it a
hundred percent. But still, ninety-nine point nine percent, you know which day
is ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, right? And you know that today in
בבל Bavel they're eating and today's really יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So
how could you not do something about it just because of this
technicality?
How much of a gap was there between the acceptance of the
עדות eidus and the
proclamation?
There's no official amount of time.
Is it minutes or hours?
It could be, look, that's the point. In practice, it probably was
hours, to do a whole cross-examination
and all. It probably a whole process. It probably took hours. That's
the point. So he left twenty minutes before, clearly there was no
time. But I think תוספות Tosos is framing it that way to
say like who knows, hypothetically maybe they would have just done it
all צ'יק צ'אק chick-chak pro forma and done it in five minutes.
Okay, but that's what the משנה Mishna of רבן שמעון...
Rabban Shimon... I understand. I understand what the general process is. But
תוספות Tosos is framing it in a way so it's not completely
absurd, so that there's a one in a million possibility they did
it צ'יק צ'אק chick-chak and even though לוי Levi left right before
sunset and actually what, fine. But even if that's true, it's not
a hundred percent. Nevertheless, it's ninety-nine point nine percent. How could you
go ahead and let them eat on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? So
here תוספות Tosos says a really shocking thing. If you take a
look, תוספות Tosos says like
this. תוספות, Tosofos, I'll tell you in a minute. ואם תאמר, Ve-im
tomar, והיכי. ve-heich. So take a look at the word והיכי, ve-heich,
that's ten lines down in the narrow
lines. והיכי יניחם לאכול ויש כאן ודאי איסור כרת דאורייתא. Ve-heich yanicham
leechol ve-yesh kan vadai issur kareis d'Oraisa. Okay, who cares about the
little technicality? You know it's יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. How do you
let them eat on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? ויש לומר, Ve-yesh lomar,
you could say, התנא כמאן פרק שני אשר תקראו אותם מקראי קודש
בין בזמנם בין שלא
בזמנם. hatna k'ma'an perek sheini, asher tikre'u osam mikra'ei kodesh, bein bizmanam
bein she-lo bizmanam. That whether this is the idea that בית דין
Beis Din could ignore, contradict the witnesses, make a day ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh. even if it's not really ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh, Like
we saw before, they could manipulate the calendar, whether by making the
witnesses lie, ignoring the witnesses, whatever they say works.
דאמרינן בגמרא, d'amrinan b'gemara, אתם אפילו שוגגים אתם אפילו מזידים אתם אפילו
מוטעים, atem afilu shogegim atem afilu mezidim afilu mut'im, whether you intentionally
get it wrong, unintentionally, you're mistaken. So therefore basically תוספות Tosos says,
here's what he's saying, a shocking thing: that it's one thing when
the central בית דין Beis Din gets it wrong but they declare
ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh. that's binding. But you know what תוספות Tosos
has just said? In ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the central בית דין
Beis Din declared one day ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. In בבל, Bavel,
they thought a different day was ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh They didn't
declare it. It wasn't a formal declaration. They were just working on
an assumption of what had happened in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But
nevertheless, since the entire Babylonian community had identified a particular day as
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, and another particular day as יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, that became binding. So for תוספות, Tosofos, you actually had a
reality where there was one day of יום כיפור Yom Kippur in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and a different day of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur in בבל Bavel because even if you make a mistake, it's
binding. Now of course we say that when you're dealing with a
central בית דין Beis Din with the one single authority for the
Jewish people. תוספות Tosos is allowing for a possibility of two calendars,
both of which are valid. And by the way, the idea of
a need for a single calendar, you can't have some people having
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah on one day and some on another, some
have יום כיפור Yom Kippur one day some on another, ultimately became
the big determinant for who where is the center of authority for
the Jewish people. Like a big issue in the period of the
גאונים Geonim was were the גאוני בבל Gaonei Bavel going to determine
the category or calendar or were the גאוני ארץ ישראל. Gaonei Eretz
Yisrael. And in the end there was a whole debate that the
גאוני ארץ ישראל Gaonei Eretz Yisrael said one particular day, גאוני בבל
Gaonei Bavel another, and it was clearly recognized you cannot have the
communities doing different calendars. And there was a huge fight who had
ultimate authority, and any guess who it was? בבל. Bavel. Because that
even though it's supposed to be the authority in ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, that was basically part of the whole shift of תורה Torah
scholarship and authority to בבל. Bavel. So תוספות Tosos is here allowing
to explain this גמרא Gemara like how could you keep quiet if
everybody's eating on יום כיפור Yom Kippur to actually say it was
possible to have two separate calendars valid at the same time. Yes.
Another way that that could work is if the International Dateline is
between ארץ ישראל...
Eretz Yisrael... That's interesting.
You need to put it somewhere.
Yes, that's interesting. Although that's not what the גמרא Gemara is saying
but that's interesting.
Okay, so you're saying that תוספות Tosofos therefore is projecting theoretically a
paradigm for the decentralization of authority.
Yeah, but in a way that the... never tolerated. We have never
tolerated two separate— I mean, if somebody had a separate calendar that
made them completely sectarians, you know, like
the...
right. Right. Okay. Alright. So now the גמרא, Gemara, let's go back.
Okay, so it's a fascinating תוספות. Tosafot. Back to the גמרא. Gemara.
So there they were. It was יום כיפור Yom Kippur in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but he refused to say anything about it or
to do anything helpful about it. Okay, yes.
In terms of chronology, in other words, this could exist but
they wouldn't have been able to have this.
Right, presumably, presumably. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מכריז רב יוחנן Machriz Rav
Yochanan and רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan declared: כל היכא דמטו שלוחי ניסן
ולא מטו שלוחי תשרי ליעבדו תרי יומי גזירה ניסן אטו תשרי. Kol
heicha d'matu shluchei Nissan v'lo matu shluchei Tishrei l'avdu trei yomei gzeira
Nissan atu Tishrei.
So this gets to the issue as where did they keep two
day? Okay, first here is ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, okay I'm going
to draw a bad picture of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, okay whatever,
I can't help it. Here is ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, okay, right?
Everybody with me? Here is ירושלים Yerushalayim making ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh,
and the שלוחין shluchin go out, okay? And the שלוחין shluchin go
out and tell everybody when it was so that they can keep,
you know, they can keep סוכות Succot and ניסן Nissan on the
right time, right? סוכות Succot and פסח. Pesach. How far do the
שלוחין shluchin get? Well, they leave now on ניסן, Nissan, they actually
can leave on א ניסן. Aleph Nissan. How many days can they
travel? They can travel before פסח, Pesach, they basically can travel, right,
14 days before פסח Pesach minus what occurs in every period of
14 days? שבתות. Shabbatot.
Okay, so for ניסן Nissan they can travel 12 days' journey, okay?
How far can they travel for תשרי? Tishrei? So when do they
leave? They don't leave on א תשרי, Aleph Tishrei, they leave on
ב תשרי. Bet Tishrei. How many days can they not travel in
addition— so that's one day less. How many days can they not
travel in addition to two שבתות? Shabbatot?
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So they can travel— they can travel two
days less. So for תשרי Tishrei they only go 10 days' journey,
okay, for תשרי. Tishrei. So all of the communities, who keeps two
day? Nobody here keeps two day. Everybody here keeps only one day
because they all find out in time for— one day, no, one
day סוכות Succot and פסח. Pesach. Okay, ראש השנה Rosh Hashana is
different, okay? Everybody here, but how about everybody here keeps two day,
because nobody here finds out in time for פסח. Pesach. How about
the people that live here? They know in time for פסח, Pesach,
but they don't know in time for סוכות, Succot, right? For פסח
Pesach they know, which day is ראש השנה Rosh Hashana they only
keep one day, for סוכות Succot they don't know and they'd have
to keep two day. So what do you do in this, in
the people that live in those places? So let's take a look.
So מכריז רב יוחנן, Machriz Rav Yochanan, so רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
proclaimed,
where were we? מכריז רב יוחנן כל היכא דמטו שלוחי ניסן ולא
מטו שלוחי תשרי ליעבדו תרי יומי גזירה ניסן אטו תשרי. Machriz Rav
Yochanan kol heicha d'matu shluchei Nissan v'lo matu shluchei Tishrei l'avdu trei
yomei gzeira Nissan atu Tishrei. Wherever the messengers of ניסן Nissan have
arrived but not the messengers of תשרי, Tishrei, ליעבדו תרי יומי, l'avdu
trei yomei, even for פסח Pesach keep two days פסח Pesach if
you're in that gap zone. Why? גזירה ניסן אטו תשרי, Gzeira Nissan
atu Tishrei, because if you only keep one day of פסח Pesach
you'll come to only keep one day of סוכות. Succot. So therefore,
we don't want to have this weird thing that some day's two
and some day's one. So if you're in this zone here, that
at least for סוכות Succot it's two days, keep two days for
פסח Pesach as well. Okay. רבי אייבו בר נגרי ורבי חייא בר
אבא איקלעו להוא אתרא. Rabbi Aibo bar Nagri v'Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba
ikla'u l'hahu atra. So these two rabbis who were students of רב
יוחנן— Rav Yochanan רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan was the man who made
this announcement— came to a particular place דהוו מטו שלוחי ניסן ולא
מטו שלוחי תשרי, d'havu matu shluchei Nissan v'lo matu shluchei Tishrei, which
was exactly in this gray zone. A place where they found out
in time for פסח, Pesach, but they didn't find out in time
for סוכות. Succot. ועבדי חד יומא. V'avdi chad yoma. They did only
one day of פסח Pesach because פסח Pesach they knew. Okay, they
didn't follow what רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan had said. ולא אמרו להו
ולא מידי. V'lo amru lehu v'lo midi.
And these two students of רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan didn't say anything.
They didn't speak up. Okay. Another story of people not speaking up,
like the לוי Levi story. But here, it's more of a rabbinic
concern. They didn't speak up, they let them do just one day
of פסח. Pesach. שמע רב יוחנן. Shma Rav Yochanan. רב יוחנן Rav
Yochanan heard that his two students tolerated this and didn't say anything
about it, ואיקפד. v'ikpad. He got upset. אמר להו. Amar lehu. He
said to his students, לאו אמינא לכו, lav amina l'chu, didn't I
tell you היכא דמטו שלוחי ניסן ולא מטו שלוחי תשרי ליעבדו תרי
יומי heicha d'matu shluchei Nissan v'lo matu shluchei Tishrei l'avdu trei yomei
that in this place where they know about it in time for
ניסן, Nissan, in time for פסח, Pesach, but not in time for
סוכות, Succot, that they need to still keep two days of פסח
Pesach because of גזירה ניסן אטו תשרי? gzeira Nissan atu Tishrei? Because
if they don't,
they have to do ניסן Nissan so that it doesn't lead to
them, because if they have to do two days of ניסן Nissan
so it shouldn't have a spillover into תשרי Tishrei and if they
do only one day פסח, Pesach, they'll do only one day סוכות.
Succot. So haven't I told you?
He heard about it after.
Right, so רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan said after that: How'd you let
them do only one day of פסח? Pesach? I told you guys
that in that place they should be doing two days of פסח
Pesach because since they have to do two days of סוכות, Succot,
they should be doing two days of פסח Pesach so they shouldn't
get confused. Okay, so and that's the end of the story. He
heard, he got upset, but that was his ruling. Okay, right. רבא,
Rava, now רבא Rava הוה רגיל דהוה יתיב בתעניתא תרי יומי. hava
ragil d'hava yateiv b'taanita trei yomei.
רבא Rava would keep two days of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. See,
things that you guys heard about the Mir Yeshiva in Shanghai, it's
already in the גמרא. Gemara. רבא, Rava, as we heard, there was
a whole story before by לוי, Levy, you never knew a hundred
percent, right, maybe it was, maybe אלול Elul was מעובר. meubar. So
רבא Rava would actually keep two days of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
זימנא חדא אשתכח כוותיה, zimna chada ishtakach k'vateih,
and one time it actually worked, he actually wound up being right.
One time it actually turned out that אלול Elul was מעובר meubar
and that for him validated his entire practice. See, all you guys
have been making fun of me all these years that I'm keeping
two days of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. This year it turned out
that it was, maybe it was the year that לוי Levy dropped
in. This year it turned out that אלול Elul was מעובר. meubar.
Oh, it shows that I'm right. Now fascinatingly you could read this
גמרא Gemara and think, oh that'll be a פרום frum thing to
do. By the way, nowadays it wouldn't be פרום frum because nowadays,
you know, we, it's a fixed calendar. The only logic of doing
this other than the ספק safek of the international date line was
when they were still, it was still in flux and you'd never
know a hundred percent, right, when אלול Elul would be, whether אלול
Elul would actually really only be twenty-nine days. Nevertheless, רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu
Chananel makes an interesting little point, even though you could have inferred,
oh maybe this is something to emulate. If you take a look
at רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, three lines down in the wide lines,
he
says, like near the end of that line, about a third from
the end, he says, דהוה ליה יום כיפור באורתא דתשרי, d'hava lei
Yom Kippur b'orta d'Tishrei, it turned out he was right that one
year, דהוה מחמיר אנפשיה, d'hava machmir anafsheih, he was being מחמיר machmir
on himself, ונקט תרי יומי, v'nakat trei yomei, ומילתא יתירה עביד, u'milta
yeteira avid,
he was just doing some like extra stringency, ולא חובה הוא עליו,
v'lo chovah hu alav,
and it was not really an obligation, שלא היה לו לחוש, shelo
hayah lo lachosh,
it's not a real reason, like we said, אלול Elul is always
twenty-nine days, there's no reason to be anxious about this and be
concerned about this, it's not a normal type of a reasonable concern,
דאם חשש מילתא
יתירה עשה ולא שובח בה, d'im chashash milta yeteira asah v'lo shubach
bah,
it was just acting like over the top and not something that
he would have
to
like praise yourself for of look how מחמיר machmir I am. Okay,
and now actually we're going to see another story
which recognizes the challenge of what it means to keep two days
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur consecutively.
If אלול Elul is thirty days, why does that mean יום כיפור
Yom Kippur is
going to be two days? No, if it's thirty days, יום כיפור
Yom Kippur will be the day after the day you think יום
כיפור Yom Kippur will be. So you're always going to keep two
days of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, because you're keeping today the tenth,
but my identifying
today Monday as the tenth assumes that ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh it
assumes that ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah was a particular day. But that
was assuming that אלול Elul was twenty-nine days. Right. But if אלול
Elul was thirty days, today isn't the tenth, it's the ninth. Right.
So Tuesday is the tenth. Right. So since I don't know, is
Monday the tenth or Tuesday the tenth, I'm going to do Monday
and Tuesday.
It's not a two day יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it's I don't
know which day is יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, so by force I
have to do both days.
I'm sorry, if he knows that ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, was the
thirtieth...
how does he know? No, he knows that, we're assuming he doesn't
know in time, you're in בבל. Bavel.
Right, right, okay. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, רב נחמן Rav Nachman יתיב בתעניתא כולי יומא דכיפורי. yateiv b'taanita
kulei yoma d'Kippurei. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman fasted the whole יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. Good to know. לאורתא, L'orta, אתא ההוא גברא, ata
hahu gavra, and the evening which was מוצאי יום כיפור, Motzaei Yom
Kippur, a person came and said to him, a person came, אמר
ליה למחר יומא רבא במערבא. amar lei lemachar yoma raba b'maarava.
So and he came, meaning I presumably it meant like right before
night, right
before it was מוצאי יום כיפור, Motzaei Yom Kippur, somebody came right
at נעילה Ne'ilah and said to him, you should be aware that
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael tomorrow is, they're starting יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, tomorrow is יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Again, three stories right in
a row: עולא, Ulla, רבא, Rava, and this story, where it wound
up, as opposed to the גמרא's Gemara statement דמימות עזרא ואילך לא
מצינו אלול מעובר, d'miyemot Ezra v'eilach lo matzinu Elul meubar, that אלול
Elul is never thirty days, we now have three stories of אלול
Elul having been thirty days and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, people having
misidentified יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So this guy came to רב נחמן
Rav Nachman and told him, you should know by the way it
was a thirty day אלול Elul and tomorrow is really יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, מהיכא
את, meiheicha at, where you coming from? אמר ליה מדמהריא, amar lei
mi'Damharia,
that was the name of the place, דמהריא. Damharia.
I'm sorry, דמהריא. Damharia.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said to him, a play
on the word דמהריא, Damharia, דם תהא אחריתיה. dam tehei acharitao.
So דם, dam, דם, dam, הריא haria like אחרית, acharit, right if
you make a guttural ה heh and guttural ח. chet. So, you
know, blood should be in your end. So or maybe blood is
as a result of you, because רש"י Rashi says this is causing
tremendous... tremendous like danger or סכנה Sakana to me or anguish to
me that I have to fast two days in a row. קרא
עליה, Karya lei, קלים היו רודפינו. Kalim hayu rodfenu.
Swift were our pursuers. You know, you came so quickly, you should
have come three days from now after it was too late. Now
you came! I don't know if that was the point, but now
you came and now I have to do tomorrow יום כיפור Yom
Kippur too. Come in a few days and then you'll tell me
and I'll worry about it then. So anyway he was very upset,
it was very challenging to fast two days straight.
Like what's the phrase, you're killing me?
You're killing me! Exactly. That's the good idiomatic expression. You're killing me,
you're killing me. All right, anyway, all right,
so שלח ליה, Shelach lei,
that's like this joke. Okay, I guess I'll tell it. Anyway, this
guy, this
Jew,
he's got this non-Jewish friend. He says, so you mean to tell
me like you would like, you know, rather, you know, you'd have
to like violate a law rather than like risk your life? He
says, yeah, absolutely. So he says, so if I were like take
a gun to your head and say like eat this cheeseburger, would
you, you know, you'd have to? He says, yeah. He says,
and if I were like take a gun to your head and
say like, okay, it's like today was שבת, Shabbat, is שבת, Shabbat,
like you have to like break שבת Shabbat now, you know, you
have to turn on a light, you'd have to? He says, yeah.
So he takes out a gun, he says, okay, turn on the
light. So like the guy sits, gets terrified, so he turns on
the light. And then his friend starts cracking up, ah, I was
just, I was just, you know, teasing, I was just kidding. And
he gets like really upset, he says, why didn't you do it
over the cheeseburger?
Okay, anyway, all right,
so somehow that then was somehow loosely associated to this. Okay, you
should have been a little bit later. Anyway, all right,
could have told me tomorrow. Anyway, שלח ליה רב הונא בר אבין
לרבא. Shelach lei Rav Huna bar Avin le-Rava. So רב הונא בר
אבין Rav Huna bar Avin sent to רבא. Rava. כד חזית דמשכה
תקופת טבת עד שיתסר בניסן. Kad chazit de-mashka tekufas Teves ad shis-asar
be-Nissan.
If you see that תקופת טבת, Tekufas Teves, which is the winter,
is extending into the 16th of ניסן, Nissan, עברה לההיא שתא. Abrah
le-hahi shata. So you have to make
a leap year, right?
Because the summer, excuse me, the spring season, solar season we're talking
here, the solar spring season has to, you know, פסח Pesach has
to fall during the spring. So if you are seeing that the
winter is going until the 16th, so פסח Pesach the 15th will
not begin in the spring. So you have to make a leap
year. Okay? So in order that פסח Pesach can begin in the
spring. ולא תחוס להם, Velo tachosh lahem, don't be concerned that that
would be improper because there's debates in another גמרא Gemara under what
circumstances can you adjust it. This obviously is a reason to make
a leap year. Okay, דכתיב, De-chtiv, as the verse says, שמור את
חודש האביב, Shamor et chodesh ha-aviv, observe the month, so חודש, Chodesh,
which is about the moon, לחדש, Le-chadesh, right? The moon makes itself
new. But it's אביב, Aviv, the spring, which is a solar period,
solar season. שמור אביב של תקופה, Shamor aviv shel tekufa, observe the
seasonal אביב, Aviv, the spring, which is a solar season. שתהא בחודש
ניסן, She-tehe be-chodesh Nissan, that it falls in the month of ניסן.
Nissan. Now it is interesting that it says the word here month,
right? That's the פסוק, Pasuk, חודש האביב, Chodesh Ha-aviv, and it doesn't
say פסח. Pesach. Because now you'd say the month, so if it's
the month, maybe the first of the month already has to be
the spring. So רש"י Rashi says no. So רש"י Rashi explains no,
because the month is determined, like we mentioned a little bit before
by analogy, the idea of חצות Chatzot by the middle of the
month. So therefore, as long as, you know, the spring begins by
the middle of the month, you are okay. Now by the way,
and therefore as long as the 15th is already in the spring,
which is פסח, Pesach, you are okay. Now by the way, you
could also tie it to the end of the פסוק, Pasuk, ועשית
פסח. Ve-asita Pesach. So פסח Pesach has to be in the spring,
but here it's connecting it to the month. Now by the way,
this issue of connecting it to the month has an implication. Because
if I told you, oh we're one day late, the spring only
begins on the 16th, we have to have the spring beginning on
the 15th, there's a much easier solution than making it a leap
year. What's the easier solution to making it a leap year? Add
an extra day to the previous month. Okay? So because of that
problem, רש"י Rashi says that it's not just that פסח Pesach has
to begin in the spring, the חודש Chodesh has to begin in
the spring. And what does חודש Chodesh mean? חודש Chodesh word from
the word of חדש, Chadash, it has to still be renewing, the
moon has to still be growing. The moon only continues to wax
until the 15th. So this, so the spring has to fall not
on the 15th but it has to fall in the 14th or
earlier. So the חודש, Chodesh, the waxing of the month, overlaps with,
you know, the spring begins within the waxing of the month. So
we can't just adjust one day and therefore we have to add
an entire month. Now the question might be, if you could predict
that, why don't you just adjust two days earlier months? So this
becomes an interesting question of how much, how much im- how much
imbalances can you allow in your calendar? A normal calendar has, right,
six thirty-day months and six twenty-nine-day months. We can go till seven
and five. Can you have as much as eight and four? So
actually
there's a question, maybe eight and four you're allowed, nine and three
you're not, according to some versions you're not even allowed eight and
four. So if you're not allowed eight and four you can't do
a double adjustment. You can only do a single adjustment. Okay, so
therefore רש״י Rashi understands that the issue is it has to be
in the fourteenth that falls in the sixteenth, we can't do an
adjustment of the month, we have to actually create a leap year.
Okay, תוספות Tosfos has a slightly different read, where תוספות Tosfos actually
says it could be in the fifteenth, it doesn't have to start
in the fourteenth, but we'll have to assume that they've already used
up their adjustments, they can't adjust it enough and therefore again a
leap year. But the basic point is the spring solar season of
the spring has to begin either by the fourteenth or the fifteenth
of ניסן, Nisan, and if it won't and you can't do it
by adjusting a month, you adjust a year.
Yes, is this the clear
foundational statement that gives the rationale for עיבור השנה? Ibur HaShana?
No, there's whole סוגיא Sugya in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, there's other סוגיות. Sugyos.
This is just one of them. But the whole point is that
we adjust for the moon, the lunar calendar, in order to adjust
the solar calendar.
Yes, and one of the major reasons is because פסח Pesach has
to be in the spring. 100%. Right. But this is not—no, this
is—this is one mention. There's a much longer discussion in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin.
Okay. All right. אמר רב נחמן להנהו נחותי ימא. Amar Rav Nachman
lehano nechusei yama. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to those that
go down, that went to the ocean, meaning seafarers, אמר להו, amar
lehu, where
I skipped a line, אתון דלא ידעיתו בקביעא דירחא, asun delo yadisu
bikviya diyarcha, you that don't know, you'll be on the sea, you'll
have no idea when בית דין Beis Din made ראש חודש, rosh
chodesh, כי חזיתו סיהרא דמשלים ליומא, ki chazisu seira demashlim leyoma,
when you see that the moon completes the day, בערו חמירא, biaru
chamira, destroy your חמץ. chametz. It's going to be פסח. Pesach. How
do you know when it's fourteenth and you have to destroy your
חמץ? chametz? When—now we would have said, well, right before the moon
gets full. Okay. Interestingly, you know, 'cause I don't know if you've
ever looked at it, like is the moon really full, is it
95% full? That's like not always 100% clear exactly how full it
is. So he gave them a different סימן siman of the middle
of the month. Rather than the moon being full, the סימן siman
he gave is that the moon
goes throughout the—the moon goes, let me see if I get this
right, if it's halfway through the month, okay, if it's halfway through
the month, that means that the sun and the moon are at
opposite, are diametrically opposite, right? Yes. And the earth is in between,
right. But this is like you, okay. So the sun and the
moon are diametrically opposite. It's the middle of the month. So right
at sunset, right, the moon rises. Yes. And right before sunrise, right
at sunrise, the moon is setting. So you will know it is
the middle of the month if the moon is visible the entire
night and then it sets as the sun is rising. Okay. So
that's what he says. He says, כי חזיתו סיהרא דמשלים ליומא, ki
chazisu seira demashlim leyoma, when you see that the moon completes the
day, meaning sort of sets, you know, as the sun is rising,
so, you know, its light finishes as the, you know, as the
day begins, then you'll know it's the middle of the month and
then בערו חמירא, biaru chamira, then destroy חמץ. chametz. Then the גמרא
Gemara says,
that's what happens in the middle of the month always? Yes. Yep.
So then the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, אימת משלים, eimas mashlim,
when does that happen, that the moon goes throughout the night and
ends when the day begins? דחמיסר, dechamisar, on the fifteenth. Okay. והנן
מארבעסר מבערינן, vahanan mearbasar mevayrinan, we have to get rid of חמץ
chametz on the fourteenth. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, לדידהו דמגלו
להו עלמא, ledidu demaglu lehu alma, for them that the world is
revealed, which means like there's a clear horizon I guess, מארבעסר משלים,
mearbasar mashlim, it happens on the fourteenth. Now Charlie can maybe tell
me what this means. What I assume it means is, you know,
I think if you're on sea level and on the ocean you
see more in terms of the curvature of the earth. Like things
that happen technically below the horizon, you're able to still see them
because you're sort of, you know, your sight line goes, you know,
sort of bends—it gets down a little bit.
If you're the other way around, if you're on like at the
top of a mountain.
Oh, then you see further down the horizon. Further down. On sea
level you don't.
So it should be the other way around.
Yeah, I don't get it because even if it's true, right, so
therefore this is what it is on the—on the fifteenth. On the
fourteenth, right, it they're a little bit not aligned yet, right, so
this is been moving backward. So on the fourteenth this is when
sunrise occurs here, then this will have set a little bit before
sunrise, right? So this will set on—on the fourteenth, right, this is
not a whole 180 degrees. So at sunrise, yes, this will set
a little bit before sunrise. So presumably what it's saying though is
that if you're looking, dipping below the horizon, it'll look like it's
setting at sunrise even though actually it'll look like. be before sunrise.
The problem I have with that is even assuming that's true in
terms of seeing the dip of the horizon, shouldn't it work in
both directions? So shouldn't it also be that sunrise starts looking like
that's happening earlier than it actually occurs since it's relative to the
sun, right? I don't sort of see how in one case you're
dipping below the horizon and the other case you're not. So I
don't really get it. But okay. Moving on. That was the end
for now for our astronomy lesson. Let's in the next five minutes
at least try to get actually we can do the next דף
*daf* the next half דף *daf* at least pretty quickly. Let us
take a look. Okay, this is stuff we've seen before. על שני
חודשים מחללין את השבת *Al shenei chadashim mechalelin et haShabbos* for two
months the messengers well when it comes to testify to the new
moon you can break שבת shabbos. *Shabbos* for to if you to
testify for any month. But when it comes to sending out the
messengers, right, the real urgency of the messengers to
is I'm sorry I got that wrong. I'm sorry. The messengers never
break שבת shabbos. *Shabbos*. I was I don't know right here we
actually were discussing how the messengers never break שבת shabbos *Shabbos*. Excuse
me. We're talking about test right messengers never break שבת *Shabbos*. Testifying
for the new moon עדים *edim* so there in principle it could
be for every month but in practice we really only did it
for ניסן nisan *Nisan* and תשרי tishrei *Tishrei* because those obviously were
the key months in terms of determining the יום טוב *Yom Tov*.
על שני חודשים מחללין את השבת *Al shenei chadashim mechalelin et haShabbos*
right I don't know why I was misstating it. Okay for two
months the witnesses can break שבת *Shabbos*, על ניסן ועל תשרי *al
Nisan ve'al Tishrei*, ניסן *Nisan* and תשרי *Tishrei*. שבהן שלוחים shluchim יוצאים
לסוריא *shebahen shluchim yotzim leSurya* that was was confusing me that's the
day because those are the days the messengers go out or those
for those months the messengers go out to סוריא *Surya* which is
like the it's the surrounding lands of Israel okay ובהן מתקנים את
המועדות *uvehen metaknin et hamoadot* and those are the months on which
all the ימים טובים *Yomim Tovim* are hinged. Those are the most
important months so for those the witnesses can break שבת *Shabbos* to
come and testify. But not for the other ones. No. So that's
the point. That's what the גמרא *Gemara* is going to
discuss. It doesn't mean that the witnesses that the messengers travel on
on שבת *Shabbos* it just means that that was the important month
for the witness for the messengers to go out. Okay really it
is all about the second statement. Not about the messengers going out
but about the מתקנים את המועדות *metaknin et hamoadot*. These were the
most important months the ימים טובים *Yomim Tovim* were dependent on them
so these are the months which the עדים *edim* can break שבת
*Shabbos* for. וכשהיה בית המקדש beis hamikdash. קיים *Ukeshehaya Beit Hamikdash kayam*
when there was a בית המקדש beis hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash* מחללין אף
על כולם מפני תקנת הקרבן *mechalelin af al kulam mipnei takanat hakorban*.
Then there were other things that were depend now the nothing is
dependent on the other months I mean okay פורים *Purim* חנוכה *Chanukah*
but you know sort of like weighty biblical things is not except
for ניסן *Nisan* and תשרי *Tishrei*. But when there was a בית
המקדש beis hamikdash, *Beit Hamikdash* there were weighty things dependent on each
month whether you bring the קרבן korban *korban* or not. So since
you want to do those months in the right astronomical time and
based on the witnesses when there was a בית המקדש beis hamikdash,
*Beit Hamikdash* you would violate שבת *Shabbos* to testify for all the
months. But without a בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* only for those two.
Let's just look quickly at the גמרא *Gemara*. על שני חודשים ותו
לא *Al shenei chadashim v'tu lo*? What do you mean two months
the witnesses the messengers would go out? רמינהו *Raminihu* we just said
in the previous משנה *Mishnah* על שישה חודשים השלוחים יוצאים *al shishah
chadashim hashluchim yotzim*. They would go out for all six months. אמר
אביי הכי קאמר *Amar Abaye hachi ka'amar*. על כולם שלוחים יוצאים מאורתא
*Al kulam shluchim yotzim me'urta*. It's true for all the months witnesses
would go out. But in the other months they would go out
already at night meaning if it was a 30 day month the
previous one right so by nightfall you would know that tomorrow's ראש
חודש rosh chodesh, *Rosh Chodesh*. We did make today ראש חודש *Rosh
Chodesh*. So for all the other months you could send them out
already at nightfall. But על ניסן ועל תשרי עד שישמעו מפי בית
דין מקודש *al Nisan ve'al Tishrei ad sheyishme'u mipi Beit Din mekudash*
which is what we had we had quoted that earlier today's דף
*daf*. על ניסן ותשרי *Al Nisan veTishrei* even though you know for
certain today is ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* because you know that yesterday
wasn't or another scenario is everybody saw the moon last night you
have no question that they're going to make today ראש חודש *Rosh
Chodesh* nevertheless because these months are so important you don't want there
to ever have been any misunderstanding and you don't want the witnesses
the messengers to go out until they explicitly hear the declaration of
מקודש *mekudash*. תניא נמי הכי *Tanya nami hachi* it's similar על כולם
יוצאים מבערב על ניסן ועל תשרי עד שישמעו מפי בית דין מקודש
*al kulam yotzim mibaerev al Nisan ve'al Tishrei ad sheyishme'u mipi Beit
Din mekudash*. And again all it really says in terms of breaking
שבת *Shabbos* is it's just another indirect proof of how important these
months are. These months are so important that all of the ימים
טובים *Yomim Tovim* are dependent on it and they wanted to make
sure that everybody heard the word מקודש *mekudash* before any report was
given so that also shows how important these months are and that's
why we break שבת *Shabbos* to bring testimony on these months. תנו
רבנן *Tanu rabanan* we taught מניין שמחללין עליהם את השבת *minayin shemechalelin
aleihem et haShabbat* how do you know you break שבת *Shabbos* testify
testify about the new moon? תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar* אלה מועדי ה'
אשר תקראו אותם במועדם *eleh moadei Hashem asher tikre'u otam bemo'adam* declare
them in their right time. So to make sure it's being declared
in their right time means that the we're going we're listening to
the witnesses and we're synchronizing our calendar to what was seen and
to the right time and it's במועדם *bemo'adam* which means it overrides
שבת *Shabbat*. יכול כשם שמחללין עד שיתקדשו כך מחללין עד שיתקיימו *Yachol
keshem shemechalelin ad sheyitkadshu kach mechalelin ad sheyitkaymu* and here's exactly the
context maybe the same way you can override שבת *Shabbos* to sanctify
so you You can override שבת to ensure its fulfillment, which means
to send out the
messengers. תלמוד לומר אשר תקראו אותם, talmud lomar asher tikre'u otam, you
declare them in their right time. על קריאתם אתה מחלל, al keri'atam
atah mechalel, on the declaring of them as ראש חודש, that happens
even on שבת. ואי אתה מחלל על קיומן, ve-ei atah mechalel al
kiyuman, not to ensure that the message gets out. But to make
it ראש חודש, that you override שבת. Last, right, last line. וכשהיה
בית המקדש קיים מחללין אף על כולן מפני תקנת הקרבן. ukheshehayah beit
hamikdash kayam mechalelin af al kulan mipenei takanat hakorban. תנו רבנן בראשונה
היו מחללין אף על כולן, tanu rabanan barishonah hayu mechalelin af al
kulan, when there was a בית המקדש. משחרב בית המקדש אמר להם
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, mishekharav beit hamikdash amar lahem raban yochanan ben
zakai, once the בית המקדש was destroyed, יוחנן בן זכאי yochanan ben
zakai said to them, whoever the them is, וכי יש קרבן? vechi
yesh korban? Is there a קרבן anymore? Why are we violating שבת
for these other months? There's no urgency, there's no weight to these
months, or serious weight. He התקינו, hitkinu, he made an establishment, שלא
יהו מחללין אלא על ניסן ועל תשרי בלבד, shelo yehu mechalelin ela
al nisan veal tishrei bilvad, only ניסן and תשרי were the ones
that continued to carry weight. I just want to say one point
about this. We always identify with יוחנן בן זכאי yochanan ben zakai
that he made all of these תקנות takannot זכר למקדש. zekher lamikdash.
If you look more closely at יוחנן בן זכאי, yochanan ben zakai,
a lot of his תקנות, takannot, and I would claim even the
ones that are ostensibly זכר למקדש, zekher lamikdash, a lot of his
תקנות takannot are actually accepting the fact that we live in a
different reality now, a post-מקדש mikdash reality, and therefore practice has to
be different. You'll remember that יוחנן בן זכאי yochanan ben zakai was
the one who went and said that we can now that there's
no בית המקדש, we can accept witnesses, right, even after מנחה mincha
time. Remember that whole thing? So here as well he's saying, no
בית המקדש, we then will stop sending out the שלוחים on the
other months. So exactly the תקנות takannot of יוחנן בן זכאי yochanan
ben zakai are sort of our responding to the post-מקדש mikdash reality,
not trying to hold on to the מקדש mikdash reality. And that's
I think an important understanding of what יוחנן בן זכאי yochanan ben
zakai and his activities were.